Guide to the New-York Historical Society Manuscripts of Lectures and Addresses 1809-1957, 2001, 2015-2016 NYHS-RG 11
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society manuscripts of lectures and addresses
1809-1957, 2001, 2015-2016
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 11
3.96 Linear feet in ten document boxes and one oversize folder
This record group principally includes a manuscript form of about 150 addresses presented at N-YHS. The bulk of these are papers read or other prepared remarks made at N-YHS from the 1840s through the 1930s. Most typically, the manuscripts are from historians and other individuals of some renown, with few from figures of national prominence. Most of the addresses concern some aspect of early New York history, particular N-YHS accomplishments, or broader reflections on the study and lessons of history and on America.
Arrangement Note
The record group is arranged in chronological order based on the date of the address, with one exception discussed below.
Information in the container list (author, title of the address, date) was taken, when present, from the manuscript itself or a covering transmittal letter from the author. When that information was not found on the manuscript, it was supplied from other sources (meeting announcement, annual report, etc.) or, in the case of titles, occasionally devised by the archivist. This supplied information is indicated in [brackets]. Information pencilled on the manuscript that appeared to have been supplied at a later date than the manuscript is also shown in [brackets]. Where there are multiple dates on the document (e.g., date written, date read, date a clean copy was forwarded to N-YHS after the address), the date read was used. An exception to this, and the arrangement generally, is the paper of William James Hubard; Hubard's paper was read posthumously to N-YHS in 1875 but was written in 1859 or 1860, and so is arranged at that earlier date.
Some of the folders hold, in addition to the address, earlier and later dated documents. Only the date of the address is used in the date range of the container list. However, a note at the folder level indicates the presence of this other material.
Accruals Note
Accruals of additional lectures and addresses are expected to be added to the record group from time to time.
Scope and Contents Note
This record group principally includes a manuscript form (i.e., not a published form) of about 150 addresses presented at N-YHS. The bulk of these are papers read or other prepared remarks made at N-YHS meetings from the 1840s through the 1930s. The period prior to 1840 is represented by only five papers, three of which are original autograph manuscripts by DeWitt Clinton (1811) and Gouverneur Morris (1812, 1816). There are only eleven documents from the period after 1937; the latest of these dates from 1957, except for three typescripts of remarks made at events in the 2000s, including those made by former U.S. President William Jefferson (Bill) Clinton.
Although 150 items is a sizable number, it represents only a small percentage of the hundreds, if not thousands, of papers and other presentations made at N-YHS meetings, special events, exhibitions, public lecture series, and other occasions. It is not known how these particular items came to be preserved in N-YHS's records, though it may have been simply a function of which papers the Librarian was able to obtain from the speaker at the time. Although a relatively small sample, the items are useful in that many have likely not been published elsewhere and in their manuscript form they give a glimpse as an artifact of the author's work and actual presentation.
Although nationally prominent figures occasionally spoke at N-YHS, this record group holds few of these. More typically, the manuscripts are from historians and others of some renown, such as George Bancroft, Benson J. Lossing, Lewis H. Morgan, Friedrich Kapp, John Austin Stevens, Jr., Oswald Garrison Villard, Horace Greeley, and Monsignor Robert Seton. Local historians also appear frequently, such as Henry Stiles, William S. Pelletreau, Hopper Striker Mott, and Reginald Pelham Bolton. Papers or remarks made by officers of N-YHS also appear, including those of Luther Bradish, Frederic De Peyster, George Gibbs, Clarence Storm, Sydney Carney, and Robert Hendre Kelby. Until the late nineteenth century the manuscripts in the record group are typically handwritten. Most manuscripts beginning in the late nineteenth century are typed. Many of the manuscripts are undated, unsigned, and untitled, so attributions have been assigned to them over time; see the arrangement note below for further discussion of how this attributed information is displayed in the container list of this finding aid.
Most of the addresses concern some aspect of United States or New York history, particularly of the colonial, Revolutionary, and early Republic periods. Some addresses relate to particular N-YHS accomplishments, such as its building dedications, centennial anniversary, and donations of objects. Other addresses, especially those offered as N-YHS's annual anniversary address, are more rhetorical with reflections on the study and lessons of history and on America more broadly. Beginning in the late 19th century, the papers were commonly presented with stereopticon illustration; many of the manuscripts indicate the images used and how they were integrated into the presentation.
In addition to the manuscripts of the addresses, many of the folders also include related documents. The presence of these additional documents is noted at the folder level. These documents include meeting announcement cards, multiple copies or versions of the address, research notes, clippings, and correspondence. One of the more substantive such files is that of William James Hubard's paper concerning his sculpture of the likeness of George Washington; this file includes correspondence and other documents related to Hubard's attempt to sell the sculpture and that place Hubard's paper in context. Several folders include research notes of John Austin Stevens, Jr. and Clarence Storm.
Biographical/Historical Note
Throughout the course of its more than 200 year history, N-YHS has been a site at which the results of historical inquiry and research have been presented. During N-YHS's first 120 years or so, a principal forum for these presentations were the regular meetings of the Society's membership, which were held several times a year. The meeting agendas typically included both business matters and the reading of a paper on a historical topic. At the conclusion of a reading, it was common for the attending members to approve a resolution thanking the speaker and requesting that a copy of the remarks be acquired for N-YHS, often for publication. Over the decades, hundreds of papers were presented at N-YHS meetings, though it does not appear from the records that manuscript copies of all of them were obtained.
The first mention in the N-YHS minutes of a discourse occurs at the September 4, 1809, meeting. Here the Reverend Doctor Samuel Miller, one of the founders of N-YHS, delivered a lecture commemorating the North American discoveries of Henry Hudson. In N-YHS's earliest years, the addresses were somewhat sporadic, often related to N-YHS anniversary observances, N-YHS presidential inaugurations, or other special events. By the 1840s, though, papers were read more routinely at meetings. Even after regular member business meetings ended in the early twentieth century as a result of a by-law change, an emphasis on holding regular lectures continued.
But N-YHS member meetings, which by the 1840s were open at least to some extent to non-members, were not the only forum for N-YHS sponsored lectures and other presentations. By the 1840s, N-YHS began to hold public lecture series outside the framework of regular business meetings, sometimes charging a fee. In addition, various special events and anniversary commemorations would call for special addresses and discourses at N-YHS or elsewhere, such as at Delmonico's restaurant. Many of these addresses would be printed in a N-YHS publication or elsewhere.
Into the early twentieth century, formal lectures and presentations, with the increasingly common use of lantern slides, were perhaps the primary activity for outreach and historical education conducted by N-YHS. But by the mid-twentieth century, as N-YHS moved into expanded quarters on Central Park West and professional practices and social conventions changed, periodic lectures became just one of many types of programs to be conducted, including talks geared to special exhibitions, school programs, tours, concerts and recitals, and so forth.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society manuscripts of lectures and addresses (NYHS-RG 11) are as follows:
The New-York Historical Society general correspondence record group (NYHS-RG 2) contains a variety of materials relating to N-YHS lectures, including proposals and direct invitation responses, scheduling and further logistical arrangements (including accompaniments such as lantern slides), updates on research and presentation topics, ephemera such as announcements and programs, discussion of events by members, and subsequent discourse on the publication of lectures. Researchers are advised to consult files within a 2-year time frame surrounding the delivery of the address at N-YHS.
New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Historians -- New York (State).; Lectures and lecturing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Speeches, addresses, etc., American -- New York (State) -- New York.; Lectures.; Manuscripts (documents); Speeches (documents); New-York Historical Society -- Archives.
- Reverend Doctor [Samuel] Miller. Discourse Commemorative of the Discovery of the Hudson, 1809 September 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents Note
  Includes a typescript of Miller's discourse, likely from the late 19th or early 20th century.
- DeWitt Clinton. Anniversary Address [Geographical, Political, and Historical View of the Indians Who Inhabited New York], 1811 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Includes Clinton's paper with notes and appendices. Includes the resolution of thanks abstracted from the minutes by Recording Secretary John Pintard.
- Gouverneur Morris. [Reflections on Prominent Historical Facts and Geographical Circumstances Which Distinguish New York], [1812 December 6] (Box 1, Folder 3)
- [Gouverneur Morris]. [Inaugural Discourse: Reflections on Lessons of History], [1816 September 4] (Box 1, Folder 4)
- [Alexander Garden]. [The Fascinating Power of Serpents], [1817 September 9] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes a photostat copy of the abstract of Garden's address as published in The American Monthly Magazine and Critical Review of November 1817, Vol III, p. 55-56. See also record group NYHS-RG 1 (New-York Historical Society management committee records), Series IV. Official Papers, for a manuscript about serpents by G. Schulte presented at the N-YHS meeting of 10 November 1818.
- George Gibbs. Description of Certain Human Skeletons Supposed to be in Armor, Found at Fall River or Troy in Massachusetts, 1840 February [March 3] (Box 1, Folder 6)
- William Beach Lawrence. Anniversary Address, 1842 [November 1] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Lawrence's remarks appear to be a survey of N-YHS's history, collections and publications.
- [Henry R. Schoolcraft]. Scientific Associations Abroad, 1842 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- C. F. [Charles Fenno] Hoffman. North American Mythology, [1843 December 5] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes handwritten prefatory remarks and the published text of the subject matter. It appears to have been published over time in three parts, though the source publication is not identified. The second part has a publication date of 14 August 1847, from a New York publication of which Hoffman was the editor.
- Thomas De Witt. New Netherland, 1844 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- [Lewis H.] Morgan. On the Territorial Limits, Geographical Names, and Trails of the Iroquois (1 of 2), [1847 May 4] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  In addition to the text of Morgan's remarks, the documents include a manuscript map of the subject territory, with a schedule of explanatory comments linked numerically to places on the map. The map and schedule were separated to the following oversize folder.
- [Lewis H.] Morgan. On the Territorial Limits, Geographical Names, and Trails of the Iroquois (2 of 2), 1847 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 14)
  Includes the oversize map and associated schedule separated from the manuscript of Lewis Morgan's paper.
- James W. Beekman. Early European Colonies on the Delaware, 1847 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Thomas Barlow. An Incident of the Revolution, 1847 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- David E. Bartlett. Language, Considered Chiefly in Reference to its Modes of Adaptation to the Understanding, 1847 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Bartlett was associated with the New York Institution for the Instruction of the Deaf and Dumb.
- James Searing [Benjamin F. Thompson, copyist]. The Battle of Ticonderoga, 1758, 1847 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Includes the text of James Searing's 1758 account as copied from the original by Benjamin Thompson, and presented to N-YHS. Includes Thompson's prefatory remarks about the manuscript.
- Oran W. Morris. Indian Names, Burial Places, Etc., 1848 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- George Copway. The Wars in Canada West by the Ojibways & Iroquois, 1648, 1848 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- [Thomas De Witt]. The Sources of Some of the Early Settlements in the State of New York, [1848 April 4] (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Guillaume Tell Poussin. Discourse [Reflections on the American Example of Democracy and on the Press], 1848 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Frederic De Peyster. The Ancient and Present Depth of Butter Milk Channel, 1848 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Frederic De Peyster. Paper Read on the Occasion of Presenting the Idol from the Ruins of Tustepeque, 1848 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- [Orsamus H. Marshall]. Champlain in the Onondaga Valley, 1849 March 2 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Read by Mr. Bartlett. See also Marshall's later paper on this subject below in October 1885.
- Nathan Burchard.Tionuniot, or the Oneida Stone, and the Remains of Indian Antiquities in its Vicinity, 1849 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- [Luther Bradish]. Annual Address [The Philosophy of History, With Some Sense of the Progress of the World During the Past Century], 1849 [November 20] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Includes two manuscript copies of Bradish's remarks.
- [Henry C. Murphy?]. On the Limits of New Netherland, [Circa 1850?] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Includes Murphy's(?) address and a manuscript translation of Adrian van der Donck's "Description of the Limits of New Netherland" (1651).
- Peter J. Van Pelt. Historical Facts in Connection with the First Settlement of the City of New York & Its Environs, Etc., 1850 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- William W. Campbell. Anniversary Address. [The Progress of Historical Research in the U.S. in the Last 25 Years], 1850 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Includes clippings of the published version of the address, with annotations, possibly from a newspaper.
- W. B. Taylor. History of the New York Post Office and Postal Arrangements, 1851 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Includes two manuscripts: a rough draft and a final.
- Edwin Williams. The Importance of a General Index to American Newspapers., 1851 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Includes clippings of a published version of Williams's remarks, likely from a newspaper.
- Chief Justice Jones and Charles O'Conor. [Motion and Second for a Resolution Thanking Daniel Webster for his Address], [1852 February] (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Pliny Miles. Icelandic History, 1853 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- William Allen. On Presenting an Aukook, or Indian Pot or Kettle, 1854 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- [Frederic De Peyster]. [On Presenting the Portrait of De Witt Clinton], 1854 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Celebration of the 50th Anniversary, 1854 November 20 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Includes drafts of the toasts, responses to the toasts, prayers, remarks, and other materials compiled to publish in the Proceedings. The documents include George Bancroft's response to the toast to him, but not his oration of the day. A portion of the printed Proceedings is in the folder.
- Henry T. Drowne. The Nocturnal, 1855 June (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Includes the paper written by Drowne and read by George H. Moore at the 5 June meeting. The folder also includes the two drawings of the nocturnal (a nautical instrument) presented by Drowne with his paper: top view and under view. Both drawn from Capt. Anthony Lewis's original instrument by his descendant and owner of the nocturnal in June 1855, John Holden Arnold.
- Frederick [Friedrich] Kapp. The Early Life and Character of General von Steuben, 1855 June 5 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Henry C. Van Schaack. Reminiscences of Egbert Benson, 1856 February 5 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Includes two manuscript copies and Van Schaack's transmittal letter to George Moore of one of the copies.
- Frederick [Friedrich] Kapp. The Hessians in the American Revolution (First Part), 1856 June 3 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- James Riker. Early Settlement of the Wallabout, 1857 May 5 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Includes two manuscript copies and Riker's transmittal letter to Andrew Warner of one of the copies. Riker's paper engages in part with the Rapelje family, their settlement at Wallabout, and the birth of Sarah Rapelje, said to be the first child of European parentage born in New York.
- Luther Bradish. Dedication of the New Fireproof Library Edifice of the New-York Historical Society, 1857 November 3 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Peter J. Van Pelt. [Dedication of the N-YHS Building], 1857 November 3 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- [Henry B. Dawson]. Retreats [of the American Army] through Westchester County in 1776 (1 of 3), [1858 April 20] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  This folder and the next two include at least two manuscript copies of Dawson's remarks, with sourced footnotes. Also includes transcriptions of source documents. A note from W.K. (likely William Kelby) indicates that the documents were purchased by N-YHS at the sale of Dawson's library on 19 May 1890. Also includes typed abstracts from documents and publications from 1861-1889 related to the Battle of Harlem Plains; one of these abstracts refers to a Dawson presentation on the subject at an N-YHS meeting of 18 June 1861.
- [Henry B. Dawson]. Retreats [of the American Army] through Westchester County in 1776 (2 of 3), [1858 April 20] (Box 2, Folder 10)
- [Henry B. Dawson]. Retreats [of the American Army] through Westchester County in 1776 (3 of 3), [1858 April 20] (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Thomas F. De Voe. An Historical Outline of All the Public Markets of the City of New York, 1858 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Includes two manuscript copies.
- [George H. Moore?]. Mr. Lee's Plan, 29 March 1777, [Circa 1858 June 22] (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Includes a transcription of a document, with George H. Moore's instructions to a printer for setting it. The document was likely used in connection with Moore's paper "Treason of Major General Charles Lee" read to N-YHS on 22 June 1858.
- [John Wakefield Francis?]. Reminiscences of Washington Irving, [1859 December 6] (Box 2, Folder 14)
- William James Hubard. Washington's Likeness and the National Standard For It, 1859-1860 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  The folder includes Hubard's paper on the subject, written in 1859 or 1860. It was not read to N-YHS until 2 March 1875, by Librarian George H. Moore. In addition, the folder includes letters from Hubard to Andrew Warner, an officer of N-YHS, concerning the paper and Hubard's sculpture of Washington. The folder holds other related correspondence and the 1860 report of the New York City Committee on Arts and Sciences recommending the purchase of Hubard's copy of Houdon's statue of Washington.
- George H. McWhorter. [W. Wright Hawkes, copyist]. Memoir of General Alexander McDougall, 1860? (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Includes the transcription of McWhorter's original taken and read by Hawkes to N-YHS.
- [Benjamin Robert Winthrop]. Old New York, [1862 February 4] (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Frederic De Peyster. Memoir of the Honorable Rip Van Dam, 1862 November 4 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Includes two manuscript copies, one of which is incomplete.
- George H. McWhorter. Recollections of the Period of the Declaration of Independence, [1863 February 17] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Paper read at the 17 February meeting by George H. Moore
- Rev. Roswell D. Hitchcock. The Life, Writings, and Character of Rev. Edward Robinson, D.D., LL.D, 1863 March 24 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- [Frederic De Peyster]. [The Inauguration of Washington in 1789]., [1864 March 1] (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Isaac J. Greenwood, Jr. Memoir of John Bailey and the War Sword of Washington, 1864 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Prof. G. [Gustavus] Seyffarth. Remarks on Prof. Anderson's Mummy-Coffins, [1864 December] (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Isaac J. Greenwood, Jr. The Montauk Indians: An Historical Sketch, 1864 December 30 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Includes a paper submitted by Greenwood to George H. Moore for the collections of N-YHS. From the document and an accompanying letter to Moore, it is not evident that the paper was read to the N-YHS.
- Henry C. Van Schaack. A Gentleman of the Old School, and a Non-a-genarian, 1865 February 7 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  The subject is Henry Van Schaack (circa 1732-1823).
- John F. Aiken. The History of Liberty, 1866 February 6 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- [Thomas Ewbank]. North American Rock-Writing and other Aboriginal Inscriptions, [1866 March 6] (Box 3, Folder 8)
  The paper was read at the 6 March meeting by George H. Moore. In addition to the paper, the folder includes an apparently unrelated copy of Ewbank's letter of December 1868 to Miss Eliza M. Ewbank of Rio de Janeiro.
- Col. J. G. [James Grant] Wilson. The Red River Dam, [1866 March 6] (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Charles C. Savage. George Bruce and His Connection with the Art of Printing, 1866 October 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  The bound text includes a tipped-in page from August 1858 with examples of George Bruce's patented scripts. Charles Savage is identified as the President of the N.Y. Typographical Society.
- S. [Solomon] Alofsen. [Saint Nicholas and His Festival in Amsterdam]., 1865-1866 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Includes correspondence from Alofsen to Librarian George Moore describing the Saint Nicholas traditions of the Netherlands, sheet music from Amsterdam with Dutch lyrics and Alofsen's annotations, and Alofsen's translation of the lyrics. The Alofsen material dates from 1865-66. Also in the folder is a 1939 reprint from N-YHS of a version of the Saint Nicholas song distributed by N-YHS in 1864 and of a broadside distributed in 1810, and photoreproductions of several of the documents.
- Evert A. Duyckinck. Memorial of Francis L. Hawks, D.D., 1866 December (Box 3, Folder 12)
  In addition to the memorial, the folder includes a bibliography of the writings of Hawks compiled at the direction of William Gowanus and forwarded by him in 1870 to Duyckinck.
- John Austin Stevens, Jr. The Merchants of New-York, 1765-1775: Non-Importation Agreements. Committee of Correspondence, 1867 June 4 (Box 3, Folder 13)